Guide to the Jay C. Waldman Papers, 1968-2003 AIS.2007.10
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Campaign for Governor Consultants, 1969-1978; III.
  Since Waldman, the designated campaign manager, had never run a campaign before, he carefully reviewed each consultant's suggestions. Waldman's own memoranda ultimately spell out the actual path of the campaign. The extensive Tarrance volumes were actually bound as books and have been maintained in that form. Additionally, information by Market Opinion Research (MOR) is included in this series and was extensively used while Thornburgh served as Governor. The material in this series dates from 1969 to 1978.
  - Communications consultants, June 22, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Patrick H. Caddell, December 10, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Robert Goodman Agency, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Triad, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Bailey Deardorff sample plan, May 1969, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - The Agency, Harkens & Uhre, July-August 1977 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - MOR, Statewide Survey, August-November 1977 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - MOR, Earlier polls, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Politicon, Campaign Strategy, May 1977 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Roger Ailes, Media Consultant, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Garth Associates, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Eddie Mahe, Campaign Plan Part I, February 1978 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Eddie Mahe, Campaign Plan Part II, February 1978 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Eddie Mahe, correspondence, June 1977-March 1978 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Pennsylvanians for Effective Government (PEG), draft Questionnaire, August 10, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - V. Lance Tarrance & Associates, Survey Political Attitudes in PA, Vol. I, October 1977 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - V. Lance Tarrance & Associates, Survey Political Attitudes in PA, Vol. II, October 1977 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - V. Lance Tarrance & Associates, Survey Political Attitudes in PA. Vol. III, October 1977 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - V. Lance Tarrance & Associates, Survey Political Attitudes in PA, Vol IV, October 1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - V. Lance Tarrance & Associates, Survey Political Attitudes in PA, Vol. V, October 1977 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - V. Lance Tarrance, Pennsylvania Aggregates Statewide Republicans, October 1977 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - V. Lance Tarrance, Draft Questionnaires, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - V. Lance Tarrance, Questionnaires, September 26, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - V. Lance Tarrance, Questionnaires, October 4, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - V. Lance Tarrance, Questionnaires, October 1977 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Campaign for Governor Opposition Research, 1955-1978; IV.
  As campaign manager Waldman kept meticulous files on other candidates in the governor's race, known familiarly as opposition research. Knowing opponents' past records, and current platform and actions can be a critical determinant in an election. The depth of material prepared and accumulated by the Thornburgh campaign staff is a testament to the thoroughness of campaign research and where "no surprises" was a mantra. It was prudent also to be knowledgeable about the primary Democratic candidates, not knowing which would be Thornburgh's opposition in a general election should he win the primary. There are clippings for each candidate, candidate assessments, plus biographical material both for Republicans and Democrats. This series is further divided into three subseries: Primary Candidates, General Election Candidate Assessments, and General Election Candidate News Clippings. The materials date from 1974 to 1978. Additional and significant material about the candidates can be found in the Dick Thornburgh Papers.
  - Primary Election Candidates, 1977-1978; 1.
    In the primary election Thornburgh was opposed by six Republican candidates, he being the only "western" candidate. This comparatively large number of candidates divided the votes considerably, and the balance between east and west candidates became a significant factor. Additionally, it is fair to say that of all the candidates in both parties, Thornburgh was perhaps the least well known across the Commonwealth. On the Democrat side, there were several candidates, again with one from Western Pennsylvania, Pete Flaherty, Pittsburgh's former Mayor. There are some preliminary "how to" files, and then the candidates are listed alphabetically, first Democrats (D) and then Republicans (R). The majority of the material in this subseries dates from 1977 to 1978.
    - Opposition Research Guidelines prepared by Republican National Committee, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Lieutenant Governor candidates, Republican and Democrat, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - News Digests about Republican and Democrat candidates for Governor, April 1978 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Robert P. Casey (D) - news clips, January-February 1978 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Robert P. Casey (D) - news clips, March-April 1978 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Pete Flaherty (D) - news clips, January-February 1978 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Pete Flaherty (D) - news clips, March-April 1978 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Ernest Kline (D) - news clips, January-February 1978 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Ernest Kline (D) - news clips, March-April 1978 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Robert Butera (R) - candidate assessment, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Robert Butera (R) - Butera Committee bulletins, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Robert Butera (R) - correspondence to and from, including Thornburgh, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Robert Butera (R) - Butera Committee brochures, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Robert Butera (R) - Finance reports, November 1977, March 1978 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Robert Butera (R) - news clips, January-February 1978 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Robert Butera (R) - news clips, March-May 1978 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Henry Hager (R) - resume, brochures, clippings, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Henry Hager (R) - news clips, January-March 1978 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Henry Hager (R) - news clips, April-May 1978 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - David Marston (R) -correspondence, bio, brochures, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - David Marston (R) - news clips, January-February 1978 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - David Marston (R) - news clips, March 1978 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - David Marston (R) - news clips, March 1978 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - David Marston (R) -news clips, April 1978 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Arlen Specter (R) - candidate assessment, correspondence to, articles, and updates, 1973-1978 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Arlen Specter (R) - Announcement and platform, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Arlen Specter (R) - Committee updates and newsletters, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Arlen Specter (R) - campaign committee brochures, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Arlen Specter (R) - committee correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Arlen Specter (R) - news clips, January-February 1978 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Arlen Specter (R) - news clips, March-May 1978 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Richard Schweiker (R) - news clips, December 1977 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Other candidates (R) - Jacobsen, Watson, January-March, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Candidates binder (R), 1978 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - General Election Candidates, 1955-1978; 2.
    This material documents the General Election Candidates and their issues. In the General Election the opposition research focused on the two principal Democrat candidates: Pete Flaherty for Governor and Robert Casey for Lieutenant Governor. That Flaherty and Casey were both from Pittsburgh presented an unusual circumstance, with Thornburgh also a Pittsburgher. Flaherty had the reputation of being a successful former Mayor of Pittsburgh and previously had run an unsuccessful campaign for U.S. Senate. Thornburgh, on the other hand, was little known outside Western Pennsylvania. Casey became the Democrat Lieutenant Governor candidate due to the coincidence of having precisely the same name (Robert P. Casey) as the former auditor general of Pennsylvania who was a gubernatorial candidate in the Primary. Running among fifteen lesser known persons, the "wrong Bob Casey" was selected, having no political or public service experience whatsoever. On the Republican side, William W. Scranton III, son of the well known and much admired former Governor, became the choice for Lieutenant Governor and actively participated in the campaign. Candidate research included Scranton as well as the Democrats since Thornburgh needed to know the background and issues important to his potential Lieutenant Governor. The major research focused on Flaherty and the background topics are those from a binder distributed to campaign staff. The Dick Thornburgh Papers contain much relevant information to this series. The materials in this subseries date from 1955 to 1978.
    - William W. Scranton III (R), biographical material, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - William W. Scranton III (R), attachments, 1972-1978 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Robert P. Casey (D), assessment, 1974-1978 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Pete Flaherty, binder memo, July 6, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Pete Flaherty, biographical, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Pete Flaherty, political career, 1955-1974 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Pete Flaherty, Pittsburgh City Councilman, 1966-1969 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Pete Flaherty, Mayor of Pittsburgh, 1965-1975 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Pete Flaherty, Mayor of Pittsburgh, 1970-1976 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Pete Flaherty, "The City, Before, During and After Pete", 1969-1978 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Pete Flaherty, US Deputy Attorney General, March-November 1977 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Pete Flaherty, political alliances, 1969-1977 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Pete Flaherty, finances, 1976-1978 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Pete Flaherty, primary issues, and general updates, 1970-1978 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Pete Flaherty, editorials and miscellaneous clips, 1969-1975 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Pete Flaherty, "A Second View," with attachments, 1969-1975 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Pete Flaherty, running for Governor, announcement, January 23, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Pete Flaherty, campaign '78, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Pete Flaherty, primary '78 contributors list, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Pete Flaherty, Flaherty-Casey finances, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - General Election Candidate News Clippings, 1978; 3.
    This series contains the newspaper clippings from the campaign and are separated by candidate and month in the original order that they were prepared and distributed to campaign staff. There are very few clippings for Robert P. Casey since he had been told by the Pete Flaherty campaign to stay teaching rather than complicate the campaign as he did the first few times he appeared with undesirable results. Ultimately it was telling that the students at his school endorsed William W. Scranton. To appreciate the specific status of the campaign, similarly dated clippings from each candidate could be reviewed and compared. There are very few articles from early November, since election day was November 7, and clippings and candidate comments were no longer useful. The material dates from May to early November 1978.
    - Scranton, May-June 1978 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Scranton, July 1978 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Scranton, September 1978 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Casey, May-June 1978 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Casey, July-October 1978 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Flaherty, May-June 1978 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Flaherty, July-August 1978 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Flaherty, September 1978 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Flaherty, October 1978 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Thornburgh, May-June 1978 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Thornburgh, July 1978 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Thornburgh, August 1978 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Thornburgh, September 1978 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Thornburgh, September 1978 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Thornburgh, October 1978 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Thornburgh, October 1978 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous clippings, November 1978 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Campaign for Governor Issues, 1966-1978; V.
  From the earliest interest in running for Governor, Thornburgh and Waldman focused on the necessity of finding precisely the right person to lead and develop issue substance. They found this in Rick Stafford, who put together staff and drew on multitudes of volunteers with expertise in varying areas of government. An issue binder was put together of all topics, carefully outlined, and a virtual library of resources brought to the campaign. Overall issues were easy to identify, but polls further honed those of particular concern to voters. Potholes and corruption were two highlighted. There is considerable issue documentation here both in the Waldman and Dick Thornburgh Papers. Waldman's "R&I" (research and issues) files are included in the topics in this series. It is important to note that there is not much research material by the Flaherty campaign, either primary or general election. Flaherty depended on his appealing persona and distance from discredited Shapp Democrats to win. Thornburgh in contrast, with Waldman's overall campaign leadership, successfully presented a solid platform derived from facts and knowledge to persuade the voters. The materials in this series date are from 1966 to 1978.
  - Campaign Research Techniques, 1969-1977 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Categories and system, December 1977 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Stafford Memos, 1977-1978 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Staff Memos, June-August 1978 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Issue reports, 1977-1978 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Garth issue requests, January 17, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Issue binder reports, 1977-1978 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Issue binder additions, 1977-1978 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Elected/appointed Attorney General, l976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Bert Lance issue, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Issues, 1977-early 1978 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Issues, by county, 1977-1978 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Issues, campaign '66, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Gun control legislation, 1967-1968 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Gun control, primary, 1977-1978 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Gun control, general, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Questionnaire responses, primary, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Questionnaire responses, general, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Issues, Philadelphia, general, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - State Government binder issues, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Philadelphia Black issues, general, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 29)
- Campaign for Governor Primary Election, 1969-1978; VI.
  Although Jay Waldman, Campaign Manager, had never before run a campaign, his strategy was followed meticulously by candidate Dick Thornburgh and aided by significant research on both issues and other candidates. Memoranda from Jay Waldman to Dick Thornburgh were pivotal. They discuss the initial feasibility of and tasks related to a possible campaign for governor. They then lay a foundation that was key to the ultimate success of both the primary and general election campaigns. There is no better way to understand this campaign than to read the memoranda primarily to and from Jay Waldman and Dick Thornburgh. Although Waldman's own specifically labeled materials are a bit thin in quantity they document the campaign progress, and ultimate success, due in large measure to Waldman's inspired leadership. This series is further divided into five subseries: Jay C. Waldman Files, Dick Thornburgh Files, GOP, County Files, and Campaign in Progress (CIP).
  - Jay C. Waldman Files, 1976-1978; 1.
    As indicated above, Waldman's memoranda advised and shaped the entire conduct of the campaign. The files document careful research about campaigns by Waldman. Waldman as manager guided and led and, therefore, did not leave as much paper documentation of his own. The staff and field organizers carried out the plans and left most of the research documentation. Waldman's other files are somewhat miscellaneous in character and thin given the overall strategy and organization. The handwritten notes are an indication of the extent of his contacts and information gathering from multiple sources, particularly via telephone conversations. Waldman's files are grouped as follows: memoranda, personal calendar, news clippings ("clippings"), correspondence, handwritten notes, "miscellaneous 1977," telephone logs, "people," polls, and "research." The materials in quotations are Waldman's own subject headings in original order. The files in this subseries date from 1976 to 1978.
    - Memoranda, March-July 1977 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Memoranda, Time Allocation, July 1977 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Memoranda from JCW, October-December 1977 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Memoranda from JCW, January-May 1978 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Personal calendar, June 1977- August 1978 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - "Clippings, miscellaneous," 1978 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence to/from, 1977-1978 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Notes, handwritten, 1977-1978 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - "Miscellaneous", 1977 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Telephone logs, October 4, 1977-November 18, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Telephone logs, October 27, 1977-February 16, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - "People", 1977 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Polls, 1976–1977 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - "Research", June 1977 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Dick Thornburgh Files, 1969-1978; 2.
    The Dick Thornburgh files are primarily from early in the campaign. The majority of the material is from 1977. By then the candidate was constantly on the trail, as the schedules included in the collection specifically indicate. This subseries contains both memos and correspondence to and from Dick Thornburgh. Many of the early memos are "To File" and represent the candidate's experiences on the campaign trail, contacts, and suggestions that might be useful to staff as the campaign proceeded. These were a primary tool in the effective communications between the candidate and Waldman in particular. The Thornburgh correspondence is from early in the campaign (1977) and in many cases responding to offers of help, especially from persons he knew or met on the campaign trail. News clippings (clippings) and magazine articles track the candidate as his name and positions became increasingly known and effective. Files are arranged as follows: memoranda, articles pre-campaign, biographical material, Thornburgh campaign clippings, correspondence to and from, speeches, and drafts. The Dick Thornburgh File material dates from 1969 to 1978.
    - Memoranda, May–December 1977 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Pre-Campaign Articles, 1969-1976 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Biographical Material, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Thornburgh Campaign Clippings, February 1978 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Thornburgh Campaign Clippings, March 1978 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Thornburgh Campaign Clippings, April 1978 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence from, 1977-1978 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence to, August 1977–March 1978 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Speeches and Testimony, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Speeches, Guidelines, and Drafts, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Speeches, Announcement Draft, and Transcript, January 1978 (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - Speeches and Position Papers, January–May, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - GOP, 1977-1978; 3.
    The Republican Party was active especially in the Thornburgh primary campaign for Governor, but also in the general election. Following eight years of a Democratic Governor, the GOP was particularly eager to have a Republican elected. The party's activity was especially useful in field organization across the state. Thornburgh had not run for office since an unsuccessful 1966 Campaign for Congress, and was from the western part of Pennsylvania; thus it was advantageous to have the GOP participate both in statewide organizing and fundraising. This was particularly true in the primary. The records in this subseries include: leadership lists, correspondence, events, fundraising, drafts, and plans. The material dates from 1977 to 1978.
    - Leadership Lists, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - State Committee Organization "Recommended", undated (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - Code of Conduct, draft, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Finances and organization, pre 1978 (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence, memos, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - DT correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 10, Folder 32)
    - GOP lists, DT annotated, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - 11 Month Plan draft, August 1977 (Box 10, Folder 34)
    - 11 Month Plan, August 1977–June 1978 (Box 10, Folder 35)
    - Haabestad and GOP for Thornburgh, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 36)
    - By-Law amendment, January–April 1978 (Box 10, Folder 37)
    - Cash reports, July–October 1978 (Box 10, Folder 38)
    - County incentive program, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 39)
    - GOP post primary county statistics, May 1978 (Box 10, Folder 40)
    - GOP lists by county, ward or district, undated (Box 10, Folder 41)
  - County Files, 1977-1978; 4.
    The county files supplied a basic source of information on campaign events, issues, schedules, and candidate appearances. The files were kept in four binders. One was Philadelphia area counties, and the remaining three most likely represent geographical or campaign organizational logic. The counties are kept together in the original order that they were held in the binders. Multiple copies of the binders were distributed to key staff and Thornburgh. The following information may be found for each county: U.S. census data, population and housing, economic profiles, wards, county statistics, principal industrial employers, media (radio/TV, newspaper), public officials, Republican officials, GOP voter registration, and election results from 1970 and 1976. There are some additional county notes and reports that were not in the binders. The materials date from 1977 to 1978.
    - Philadelphia area, Philadelphia, Delaware, Montgomery, Bucks, and Chester, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Armstrong, Beaver, Butler, and Center, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Clarion, Fayette, Greene, and Indiana, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Lawrence, Lycoming, Mercer, and Northumberland, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Schuylkill, Somerset, Venango, Washington, and Westmoreland, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Adams, Bedford, Bradford, and Cameron, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Carbon, Clearfield, Clinton, Columbia, and Crawford, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Elk, Forest, Franklin, Fulton, and Huntington, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Jefferson, Juniata, Lebanon, and McKean, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Mifflin, Montour, Monroe, Perry, Pike, and Potter, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Allegheny, Erie, and Blair, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Berks, Cumberland, and Cambria, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Dauphin, Lackawanna, and Lancaster, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Lehigh, Luzerne, Northampton, and York, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Notes on County lists ranked by GOP registration with time allocation, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Notes on York, Lehigh, Luzerne, and Allentown-Bethlehem-Easton, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Notes on Allegheny County, undated (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Notes on Dauphin, Cumberland, Blair, and Lackawanna, December 1977 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Notes on Berks, Lancaster, and Northampton, January 1978 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Notes on Philadelphia, January 1978 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Notes on Dauphin, Cumberland, and Blair, undated (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Campaign-in-Progress (CIP), 1972-1978; 5.